In Python, a for loop is designed to iterate over
a sequence, collection, or data structure, such
as a list, tuple, or string. Unlike a while loop,
which runs as long as a certain condition is true,
a for loop runs for a predetermined number of
iterations based on the length of the collection.
For our first example, we will use a for loop
to track a player moving through a series of 10
positions on a game grid. In this 222-for file,
we have, on line 1, a position variable set to
the number of positions, 10. The for statement
starts on line 2. P is a variable we are just
using while inside the for loop, and the range
signifies the number of times the loop should run,
which in this case is 10. Line 3 is indented and
contains a print statement to tell the game player
what position has been reached. I will run this
code and we see something quite interesting in the
results. The loop ran 10 times, as expected, but
look at the numbers we see within these results.
The positions are 0 through 9, not 1 through
10. As is the case with getting items in lists,
for loops are also zero-based by default. However,
with a slight change to the range, we can get the
numbers 1 through 10 as desired in this code. On
line 2, I will add a 1 inside the parentheses and
a comma to indicate that I want this range
to start at 1, not 0. Then, to get the loop
to run to position 10, I will add +1 to the end of
positions. These changes will shift the range from
0 to 9 to 1 to 10. I will rerun this code, and
we see the changes as expected. There is one more
argument we can add to the range of a for loop: a
step which tells the loop to run in gaps based on
the step number indicated. For example, if I add
a comma and a 2 after the positions+1 part of the
range and then rerun the code, the loop starts
at 1 and then steps 2 numbers forward with each
iteration of the loop. In a quiz situation,
this type of loop can work if one wants to,
for example, ask every other question from a pool
of questions. Knowing the for loop is important as
one needs to know when a block of code needs
to be run a set number of times, as not all
loops are conditional. To see the other type
of for example, which iterates through a list,
let’s look at this 222-for-each file, which starts
with, on line 1, a tuple of coins a player has in
a game. Then, on line 2, we see a for loop with a
new variable, coin, that is used to retrieve the
coins we see on line 1. This word can be any word
or letter, but as a good practice, people tend to
use the singular version of a word in a for loop
to loop through a plural version of the variable
that stores a list type. The code on line 3 is
indented as part of the loop and contains a print
statement that concatenates text around the coin
variable. We have three coins, so this loop should
run three times, and when I run this code, that is
exactly what happens. Again, for loops can be used
to run a block of code a set number of times or
iterate through a list such as this list of coins.